The next section that we want to discuss
concerns macrocytic anemia.
Now in macrocytic anemia, the idea is that
the patient develops an anemia, however,
the red blood cells are relatively bigger than normal.
Recall that the normal MCV is about 80 to 100,
and in a macrocytic anemia, the MCV is greater than 100.
We can ask ourselves, well, why would the MCV be big?
Or in other words, what's driving the cells to be large?
And the answer goes back to the paradigm
that we've already established in our discussion
of microcytic anemia.
Remember that I told you that in microcytic anemia,
the idea was that we started with a red blood cell precursor
in the bone marrow, and that that red blood cell precursor
in the bone marrow divides, divides, and divides,
and divides several times until it eventually
produces mature red blood cells.
Recall that I said that the red blood cell precursor
is a relatively large cell, and that each
time it divides, it becomes slightly smaller.
Now in a microcytic anemia, it's as if an extra division
occurs, making the cells just a little bit smaller than usual.
Well, in a macrocytic anemia, it's as if one less division
occurs, and when one less division occurs, the cells are going
to be larger than normal, and hence the MCV will be greater
than 100.
We can then ask the question, why would one less division occur?
And the answer here is that in a macrocytic anemia, there is usually
an upset in the production of DNA precursors.
Now remember that every time a cell divides, it requires DNA
precursors because each division requires a copying of the nucleus.
And so if there's a disruption in DNA precursors, the cell won't be
able to divide because it doesn't have the necessary precursors to
copy the nucleus.
One less division will occur, resulting in a macrocytic anemia.
Now this then raises the question of what are the major causes of
macrocytic anemia.
And of course, the major causes of macrocytic anemia will be those that
are related to the production of DNA precursors.
And so the two most common causes are folate deficiency and vitamin B12
deficiency.
Remember from biochemistry that both folate and vitamin B12 are necessary
for the synthesis of DNA precursor molecules.
And if folate or vitamin B12 is deficient, we won't be able to generate
appropriate DNA precursor molecules.
Decrease in DNA precursor molecules is going to lead to an inability of the
cell to divide one extra time, which is then going to lead to a large red blood
cell or a macrocytic red blood cell.
Here we can take a step back and remind ourselves of a little bit of biochemistry.
Remember that folate, when it comes into the body, comes into the body as tetrahydrofolate,
and it is quickly methylated, and I'll just abbreviate this with an M here.
Again, when folate comes into the body as tetrahydrofolate, it's quickly methylated.
Now, in order for tetrahydrofolate to go and to participate in the synthesis of DNA precursors,
it needs to lose this methyl group.
And so very quickly, folate will basically convince vitamin B12 to take the methyl group.
And so vitamin B12 will actually take this methyl group, tetrahydrofolate will lose the methyl
group, allowing tetrahydrofolate to participate in DNA precursor synthesis.
Now, once vitamin B12 takes the methyl group, it's as if vitamin B12 recognizes, hey, this
methyl group is not cool, I need to get rid of it, and it very quickly passes it on to
another molecule.
And that molecule that it passes it on to is homocysteine.
Now, homocysteine accepts the methyl group, and when homocysteine accepts the methyl group,
it becomes methionine.
And of course, you're well aware from biochemistry that methionine is important in the transfer
of methyl groups to various other important molecules, but we don't have time to discuss
that here.
That's more of a biochemistry notion.
So again, general principle, tetrahydrofolate needs to lose the methyl group to participate
in DNA precursor synthesis.
It hands the methyl group to vitamin B12, vitamin B12 then hands it to homocysteine.
Now, imagine if there is a folate deficiency, if folate is knocked out, then obviously DNA
precursors won't be made.
And also, if vitamin B12 is missing, tetrahydrofolate won't be able to pass this methyl group to vitamin
B12, and hence it will also not be able to participate in DNA precursor synthesis.
And once you understand that, it's now easy to understand why I said that anemia, a macrocytic
anemia, is most commonly due to folate or vitamin B12 deficiency.
Now it's worth taking a moment here to just understand a little bit of terminology.
And that is, when we have a folate or B12 deficiency, then the term that we apply to that anemia is
called a megaloblastic anemia.
And it's called a megaloblastic anemia because folate and vitamin B12 are obviously important
for DNA, for synthesis of DNA precursors.
And if we can't produce DNA precursors appropriately, not only will the red blood cells be affected,
but other cells in the body that are rapidly dividing will also be affected.
And so those cells can become big, i.e., the cells that are rapidly dividing can become big,
and so it's called a megaloblastic anemia.
So that's an important distinction in terminology.
There are some macrocytic anemias that are not due to folate or vitamin B12 deficiency,
and we'll briefly touch on those a little bit later.
So now I think with that background, we can walk through the slides.
So here I've told you in your text that folate and vitamin B12 are necessary for synthesis
of DNA precursors.
Recall that folate, when it comes into the body as tetrahydrofolate, it gets methylated.
The methyl group must be given to vitamin B12 before tetrahydrofolate can participate
in the synthesis of DNA precursors.
So therefore, both folate and vitamin B12 are necessary for this synthesis of DNA precursors.
A lack of folate or a lack of vitamin B12 is obviously going to impair the synthesis of
DNA precursors, and then that will result in certain changes.
We'll get a megaloblastic anemia with macrocytic red blood cells with an MCV greater than 100.
Also characteristic of vitamin B12 or folate deficiency will be hypersegmented neutrophils.
Hypersegmented neutrophils refer to neutrophils that have greater than five lobes.
Now normally the nucleus of the neutrophil has anywhere from three to five lobes and greater
than five lobes indicates that we're dealing with a hypersegmented neutrophil.
Another change that we're going to see if folate or B12 is deficient is megaloblastic change
in all rapidly dividing cells.
So for example, if we were to look at the gut, we would see enlargement of the epithelial
cells within the gut.
Here's a picture of a hypersegmented neutrophil, and basically the notion here is that this
neutrophil has one, two, three, four, five, six, seven lobes, and again anything greater
than five is abnormal.
In addition, you'll notice that most of these red blood cells are relatively normal in size,
but you can see that there's a large red blood cell here, and this would be an example of
a macroovallocyte, which is again a large red blood cell that would have an MCV greater
than 100, but tends to have a little bit of an oval shape to it.
These changes, both of these, the macrocytic cell along with the hypersegmented neutrophil,
are classic findings in a megaloblastic anemia, which would be due to folate or vitamin B12
deficiency.
If you have a macrocytic anemia due to other than folate or B12 deficiency, then we would
just simply call that a macrocytic anemia.
We would not call that a megaloblastic anemia.
And so a few other causes of macrocytic anemia to be familiar with include alcoholism, this
gives you a macrocytic anemia, liver disease can cause a macrocytic anemia, and there are certain
drugs, for example, 5-FU, that can cause a macrocytic anemia.
In the case of macrocytic anemia, we would see large red blood cells with an MCV greater
than 100, however, we would not see hypersegmented neutrophils, and we would not see megaloblastic
change in the other rapidly dividing cells.
That's the distinction between megaloblastic anemia and a macrocytic anemia.
We're going to focus, obviously, on the two major causes of megaloblastic anemia.
And the first is folate.
Folate is the most common cause of a macrocytic or megaloblastic anemia, and so we want to
understand a little bit about folate, in particular its biochemistry.
Recall that folate is obtained from green vegetables and fruits, i.e., it's obtained from the diet,
and it's absorbed in the jejunum.
It is important for the purposes of examinations to know where folate is absorbed.
Folate deficiency usually develops within months, and that's because the body stores are minimal.
There is not much folate that is stored within the body.
What are some causes of folate deficiency?
Poor diet.
Again, we have limited stores, and folate is obtained from the diet, so individuals with
a poor diet will have an increased risk of developing folate deficiency.
The classic examples are alcoholics, who tend to have a poor diet, and the elderly.
Another way by which folate deficiency can arise is by increased demand.
For example, if a woman is pregnant, she's making a baby, and each cell of the baby is
going to have nuclear material, so folate would be necessary.
If a patient has cancer, and cancer is generating cells that have nuclear material, folate would be
necessary.
And hemolytic anemia, where patients are rapidly turning over their bone marrow cells, would
require an increased amount of folate.
So increased demand can also cause a folate deficiency.
And the final way, or a third way, I should say, by which folate deficiency can arise is
via folate antagonists.
Now, recall that methotrexate from pharmacology inhibits dihydrofolate reductase, that's important
to know.
Methotrexate inhibits dihydrofolate reductase, which can then result in a folate deficiency.
And so these are some important causes of folate deficiency.
When a patient becomes folate deficient, there are certain clinical and laboratory findings
that would arise.
Obviously, the patients would have a macrocytic anemia, i.e., the cells would have an MCV greater
than 100, and we would see hypersegmented neutrophils on blood smear.
In addition, the patients classically have glossitis, which is inflammation of the tongue,
and that partially has to do with the fact that the cells of the tongue are not going
to be turning over as well, and so there will be discomfort in the tongue.
There will be a decreased serum folate.
I don't think that's hard to understand.
We're dealing with folate deficiency, and so in folate deficiency, the serum folate will
be low.
There will be an increased serum homocysteine, and this is very important.
Recall that I told you that tetrahydrofolate gains a methyl group when it gets absorbed
into the human body.
It then passes that methyl group onto vitamin B12, and then vitamin B12 then passes that
methyl group onto homocysteine.
And so imagine that if there is no folate, then there is no passing of methyl to vitamin
B12, then vitamin B12 cannot pass the methyl group to homocysteine to produce methionine,
and so if homocysteine cannot become transferred, cannot be converted to methionine, then homocysteine
is going to pile up or build up, and so there will be an increase in the serum homocysteine.
And because this ties into biochemistry, and because it's useful clinically, it is important
to know.
The final clinical laboratory finding is actually a negative finding, but it's a helpful finding,
and that is that the methylmalonic acid levels will be normal.
Now methylmalonic acid gets converted to succinyl-CoA, and the mechanism by which that conversion
occurs is via vitamin B12.
Otherwise stated, vitamin B12 is necessary to convert methylmalonic acid to succinyl-CoA.
Methylmalonic acid will be normal in these patients because this is not a vitamin B12 deficiency.
We're discussing folate deficiency.
But again, it's an important negative finding because when you have a megaloblastic anemia,
the differential diagnosis would be folate or vitamin B12, and by seeing a normal methylmalonic
acid, we would gain an understanding that the vitamin B12 levels are normal.
Of course, we could also measure the vitamin B12 levels directly as well.
That then brings us into a discussion of the second cause of megaloblastic anemia, and that
is vitamin B12 deficiency.
So let's discuss a little bit of the biochemistry of vitamin B12 in order to gain a better understanding
of how a patient can become vitamin B12 deficient and hence develop a megaloblastic anemia.
Vitamin B12 is complex to animal-derived proteins, for example, meat or eggs, and it comes into
the body attached to those animal-derived proteins.
Once it comes into the body, however, vitamin B12 will be cleaved from those animal proteins
and will be bound by a protein called R binder.
Now R binder is actually produced by the salivary gland, and so the salivary gland has the job
of producing this protein that will then be complex to vitamin B12.
R binder and vitamin B12 will then travel through the esophagus and travel through the stomach
until eventually they reach the small bowel.
When they reach the small bowel, R binder will be cleaved away from vitamin B12, and how
is that going to occur?
Via the proteases that are produced by the pancreas.
Once vitamin B12 is cleaved away from R binder, vitamin B12 will then, in the intestine, bind intrinsic
factor.
An intrinsic factor is a protein that's produced by the parietal cells in the body of the stomach.
Again intrinsic factor is a protein that's produced by the parietal cells in the body
of the stomach.
Once intrinsic factor binds vitamin B12, this complex will then go to the ileum and it will
be absorbed in the ileum.
This is the basic understanding of how vitamin B12 comes into the body.
Vitamin B12 deficiency is less common than folate deficiency.
And in addition, it takes years to develop a vitamin B12 deficiency.
Why does it take years?
Because there are large hepatic stores.
The liver is loaded with vitamin B12, and so if a patient were to absolutely not see any
animal protein, for example, a vegan, a very strict vegan who doesn't take milk, doesn't
take eggs, etc., that individual could become vitamin B12 deficient.
However, it would take years to develop due to large hepatic stores of vitamin B12.
The most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency is pernicious anemia.
Pernicious anemia is a disease that arises when there is autoimmune destruction of the parietal
cells.
Remind ourselves that the parietal cells are present in the body of the stomach and they
produce intrinsic factor.
Recall that intrinsic factor is necessary to bind vitamin B12 because the ileum recognizes
the vitamin B12 intrinsic factor complex and that is what is absorbed by the ileum.
So if there is a loss of the parietal cells, there will be a loss of intrinsic factor.
And if there is a loss of intrinsic factor, there will be an inability to take up vitamin
B12 and so the patients will become vitamin B12 deficient.
And this happens to be the most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency.
I'd like to take a step back here and also remind ourselves a little bit about the parietal
cells of the stomach.
The way I think about the parietal cells of the stomach is that it's associated with
a bunch of P's.
So obviously parietal cell begins with the letter P, but in addition, the parietal cells
are the ones that have the proton pumps.
They are the ones that make the acid in the body of the stomach.
In addition, the parietal cells are pink, so that's another P.
And what do I mean by pink?
When you look at the histology of the body of the stomach, you'll see chief cells and
parietal cells.
The chief cells look more blue and the parietal cells look more pink.
And then the third P is that the parietal cells are associated with pernicious anemia.
When you knock out the parietal cells due to autoimmune destruction, that results in
pernicious anemia.
There are some other causes of vitamin B deficiency and examiners like to go after these because
they allow the examiners to test you on the biochemistry of vitamin B12 absorption.
So, for example, pancreatic insufficiency could result in a vitamin B12 deficiency.
Why would this happen?
Because remember that the pancreas produces the enzymes necessary to cleave vitamin B12
away from our binder.
Go back and remind ourselves that vitamin B12 comes into the body, is then bound by our
binder in the mouth, which is produced by the salivary glands.
The R binder vitamin B12 complex then goes through the stomach and then goes into the small bowel.
And it's in the small bowel that the pancreatic enzymes, particularly the proteases, will cleave
away our binder, which will then allow intrinsic factor to bind vitamin B12.
If there's pancreatic insufficiency and the enzymes are not produced properly, this could
result in a vitamin B12 deficiency.
So that would be one additional cause of vitamin B12 deficiency.
Another cause of vitamin B12 deficiency would be damage to the terminal ileum.
Remember that vitamin B12 is absorbed in the ileum.
And so if there's damage, for example, to the terminal ileum, as would be seen in Crohn's
disease or as would be seen with fish tapeworm, then that would result in a vitamin B12 deficiency.
A third cause that I've listed here is dietary deficiency.
Recall, and I would like to really hit home on this point because, again, examiners like
to go after it, it's very rare to see dietary deficiency except in vegans.
And what are vegans?
These are strict vegetarians that do not eat anything that comes from an animal.
So for example, they will not eat an egg.
That could then lead to a dietary deficiency.
The clinical and laboratory findings of vitamin B12 deficiency are much of what we've already
covered.
So for example, there will be a macrocytic anemia with an MCV greater than 100 with hypersegmented
neutrophils.
There will also be glossitis due to poor turnover of the cells of the surface of the tongue.
And third, and very important in the context of this discussion, is that the patients can
get a subacute combined degeneration of the spinal cord.
Recall from biochemistry that there are only two chemical reactions that vitamin B12 is
involved in.
One is the reaction that involves a synthesis of DNA precursors.
Remember that folate transfers its methyl group to vitamin B12.
The second is the conversion of methylmalonic acid to succinyl-CoA.
This reaction requires vitamin B12.
If vitamin B12 is lacking, methylmalonic acid cannot be converted to succinyl-CoA and methylmalonic
acid will then subsequently build up, in particular, within the myelin of the spinal cord.
And as it builds up within the myelin of the spinal cord, it will cause degeneration of that,
of certain regions of the spinal cord.
And that's called subacute combined degeneration of the spinal cord.
It's very important to remember that vitamin B12 is associated with this neurologic finding,
and that this finding would not be seen in folate deficiency.
Laboratory findings would include a decrease in serum vitamin B12.
In addition, there would be an increase in serum homocysteine, same concept.
If you have tetrahydrofolate, which is folate that comes into the body, it quickly gets methylated.
After that methyl group gets attached to vitamin B12, and then vitamin B12 eventually takes that
methyl group and passes it on to homocysteine.
And homocysteine will then get converted to methionine.
So if vitamin B12 is not present, it will not be able to pass this methyl group to homocysteine,
and so homocysteine levels will rise.
And so the serum homocysteine will be high.
The third lab finding would be an increase in methylmalonic acid.
And I've already explained that vitamin B12 is necessary to convert methylmalonic acid to succinyl-CoA.
And, of course, that methylmalonic acid, as it builds up, will eventually damage the spinal cord.
And that concludes our discussion of macrocytic anemia.